howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is gar alpervitz gar is a
founding principal of democracy
collaborative and has had a
distinguished career as a historian
political economist activist writer and
government
official he has served as a professor at
the university of maryland
as a former fellow of king's college
cambridge university
harvard's institute of politics the
institute for policy studies
and a guest scholar at the brookings
institute he's also president of the
national
center for economic and security
alternatives
hi garg great to have you on the show
today
uh good to be with you jim yeah we're
going to explore garr's ideas about
potential paths forward towards
systemic change in our political and
economic systems
much of it's going to come from his very
readable book
what then must we do a book i'd suggest
folks that find this podcast interesting
ought to check
out as usual we'll have links to the
book on our episode page
and when gar says systemic he means it
the word system or systemic appears 299
times in the book
cigar let's start with what do you mean
by the system
and at what scale are you referring when
you say systemic
change well uh thanks i didn't realize
what the term appeared that well
that many times thanks for checking it
jim well
let me say this i've i've worked in the
house and the senate as a
as a kind of policy director and also at
very high levels of the
government state department doing policy
policy
assumes the existing institutions in the
united states that's
dominated by corporations and to a
lesser degree by
nonprofits like universities and some
hospitals and many non-profit
organizations
and labor unions those are all
institutions
a system a political economic system
is comprised of the mix of the different
institutions
so for instance traditional what we call
communism or
state socialism or non-democratic state
socialism
the government owns the economic
institutions
and that's the kind of fundamental
design of the system
there are theorists there's never never
seen much
of a except in yugoslavia briefly who
say systems ought to be built around the
workers owning everything as
worker-owned companies those
institutions would be
at the basis of the system traditionally
in the united states
a the system is corporate capitalist
in nature but heavily organized with
unions
which are institutional part of the the
system design and they have political
economic power
and they help create legislation uh so
that's a
social democratic or welfare state
systemic
design so you begin to see the pattern
who owns and who controls and what are
the power relationships for different
kinds of institutions
and one of the arguments is we are now
entering a period
when long decaying economic social
ecological
and other trends and by comparison with
european nations very
very limited weak trends on almost every
indicator of the united states is well
below many european countries
and that systemic design that we live in
and take for granted
is more and more in question
historically
it's not producing the economic
ecological distributive
uh outcomes even liberty outcomes
compared with the goals and
values that people urge for that pattern
of
institutional putting together into a
systemic
design so it raises really traditional
questions
uh and they're very modern questions
because technology has changed so much
what
and you want to put it this way if you
don't like state socialism
and if corporation-dominated capitalism
has more and more flaws
particularly as its counterweight
in unions the counterbalance or
countervailing power is
john kenneth galbraith called it
declines to almost nothing in the united
states
the labor unions in sweden to balance
off the swedish system
in its systemic design were 80 percent
of the labor force
both economically and politically
in the united states they never got over
in the private sector now they're down
to six percent
so a very weak institutional balance
compared with
corporate power uh at six percent now
uh it makes for a very very odd and kind
of
unwieldy systemic design in which
corporations have far more power
and of course in the united states where
the working people are split by race
it makes for divide and conquer politics
and one final thing i'll throw in and we
can have a long discussion
the other part of the system design in
the united states
and people don't think about it or they
take it for granted
is very very large geographic scale
which has political implications uh
madison
james madison thought big scale was
great because you could divide and
conquer the
working classes he was very blunt about
it uh he thought if it went too far you
get tyranny but by and large it would
allow the
elites who at the outset of the american
experiment
were the only ones only property holders
could vote and he was very clear about
it the divide and conquer was
an important strategy so so that the
folks
who didn't have any landed or economic
power wouldn't be able to
organize very well um he said it could
go to tyranny if they went too far but
he thought
he could keep a nice balance that would
keep things in hand
in democracy well the continental system
you can is a big one
and it makes for an easier division
leaving aside the
very strange design that gives a state
like
political economic design systemic
design gives a state like montana
or wyoming with 600 000 people
of the same power in the united states
senate as a state like california with
30 40 million people depending upon
the estimates where they will be at the
next stage
it's a very very large and the same
number of senators so these are all
elements in how the economics and the
political structure
of the overall systemic design are
organized
and who they benefit and what results
you get and what the trends
indicate are the outcomes of different
systemic designs
so i'm opening up a lot of big questions
i know but we have a whole project that
looks at
and has been writing papers and having
conferences at harvard and mit
and the university of california
university of wisconsin
on systemic design as a major question
as we go further and further
into the century and as we have more and
more problems that don't seem to be
solved
by the current design yeah so i'll point
out to our audience there's a
nice summary of that work at the
nextsystem.org website
a lot of good stuff there and i think
that's associated with your efforts as
well if i'm correct
yes it is i'm co-chair of that project
it looks
extremely interesting i'm involved with
a project called the game b
effort which is also looking at a
systemic redesign of our social
operating system
comes from a different perspective but
i'll mention game b a couple of times
along the way probably to compare and
contrast
though actually as i read your book and
read a lot of your materials i think
there's more compare than there is
contrast
very similar i think we're both very
interested in a bottom-up
top-down simultaneous reworking of our
systems
and you call it out you know our systems
are not working some people call it
legitimacy crisis where literally
more people every year are prepared to
walk away from the system
you know one of the things i was going
to point out in fact i will point it out
is that your book
what then must we do written i think was
in 2013
had a series of possible options for the
future and one of them was so-called
option
four which started off as it's also
possible that growing social and
economic decay
will lead to one or another form of
violence on either the left
or the right or both well it seems like
we're there
right now both sides are out in the
street at least at a low level
starting to kill each other so the
number of people that are
no longer willing to proceed by normal
political means
seems to be growing by the day in
addition to your
state socialism and financial corporate
capitalism might also throw out a third
system that's being tried and that's the
chinese neo-fascist system
kind of ironic they originally were
marxist leninists but if you line up
where they are today they look a hell of
a lot like a neo-fascist system
you know combining state capitalist
cooperation
militarism racism authoritarianism
etc so i think that one's actually
another challenge
in our face that if we don't get our act
together and if we continue to decay
it may well be that chinese neo-fascism
could be the dominant system in the
world
that's exactly right they took their
model from pinochet's uh
chile they like they like the design
that he was designing
large corporations plus fascism
basically
and they studied the chilean and were
very admiring of it and then they put
some
fringes and the details into it but
that's where they got their model
yep indeed and you know talk about this
crisis of legitimacy no surprise
as you said real wages for 80 of
americans have hardly gone up
in the last three decades i actually did
a little look on it
in some statistics i have access to and
looks like the top one percent has
tripled since 1970 and the top .01
percent
has grown by 8x no wonder the people are
pissed off
right yeah you know the thing jim that i
i would
i think you would agree with this but i
want to make it clear
system design or systemic design becomes
very abstract for most people
but in fact it's very practical uh this
and very common in world history that
people begin saying hey there's
something wrong with the system
and they begin debating well what do we
do about it politically and then there's
a debate about
what are the elements for instance
there's an awful lot of
interest in worker-owned com
cooperatives as a one
kind of foundational institution at the
grassroots level
or do you want to have municipal
utilities to replace
private companies that may or may not be
polluting more
or what do you do about the big ones
like the tennessee valley authority is a
regional
public quasi-public uh entity for
regional river management and energy
control
things like that become practical
examples of how do you
think about different systems or
neighborhoods what's called a land
trust kind of draw a circle around some
of the land ownerships
to prevent excessive inflation of
housing costs
and set up a community or neighborhood
owned
structure that holds down housing costs
these are very practical elements
in a larger systemic design and it's
always important to get it away from
too abstract than idea we try to operate
at the level
in our next system project big debate
about theory and there's a lot of
theories of what
what makes for a better design what
doesn't but also
what can you do on the ground and point
to that is very very practical
and as a starting point or an element
that you can
actually show would be better than some
other elements in a systemic design
so that's what we're doing and that's
what that the book you're talking about
what that must we do
is all about and other books i've
written on this subject and our next
system project
has many many papers and academic
discussions at harvard and mit
getting very serious about this rather
than just um you know one-off
discussions yeah i think this is the you
know a very key part of the awakening
process is that people have to
understand that our
institutional structures are something
humans have created
these were not brought down from mount
sinai by moses on stone tablets
you know every single one of these
institutions we has has been
either the result of conscious design or
a series of evolutionary accidents and
typically
a combination of both you talk about
people sitting down and thinking through
new systems you know
the founding of the united states was a
perfect example
go back and read the federalist papers
the anti-federalist papers and other
works from that era
and you realize these people did a
tremendous amount of research in the
history of republics and they
had seen from history most forms of
republics had not worked and they tried
to take lessons from
you know the ones that sort of worked or
worked for a while
and combined them to the best that they
could and come up with an architecture
which surprisingly is
still working sort of 230 years later
of course it's not surprising that 230
years later a constitution that was
written and it's important to remember
when it was written
it was written when the biggest company
in the united states had 100 employees
it was a shipyard in philadelphia
it was before fossil fuels the first
coal mine in the united states was in
so we were literally living right at the
boundary
just before the beginning of the modern
age and so it's no surprise that our
political institutions
are getting very very creaky which gets
me to my
next point which you address quite well
and that's the question about well
despite its failings and it's the fact
that it's 230 years old
what about the regular political process
why can't we rely on
you know having elections voting in the
congressmen and senators that will
do what's right for the country as a way
to move forward
here into the 21st century you basically
lay out the fact that there were two
exceptional events in the 20th century
that allowed a lot of our pro-social
legislation to occur
and those two are unlikely to be
repeated maybe you could talk to us a
little bit about that
yeah let's start at one end i mean it's
it's kind of
some points are really obvious that
people know but don't kind of
think about big corporations have
enormous political power
obviously so when they donate to
campaigns they lobby
i used to work in the house and senate
and you know the lobbyists
come in with the campaign contributions
and they come in and
with wonderfully developed legislation
they say here it's already written out
you can
the congressman or the senator can just
use this material they come in with
well-briefed speeches written then they
contribute to campaigns
and it used to be that labor sort of
balanced them but
as i mentioned earlier one of the big
big changes is labor unions are down to
very minor minor part of the system now
so they they don't counter veil as
john kenneth galbraith used to say
they're just very weak and that's a real
problem
so secondly the these institutions
play a big role in putting forward what
we call legislation
they they they aren't neutral the system
and the constitution reflects
their power it it isn't like they're
over here in the
government's over there there's a real
and you know all political
is about how powerful institutions are
in the creation of what the outcomes of
the constitutional system is and also
the design of the constitution
so that's what happens then what happens
if the
labor unions disappear and the
corporations are about all you've got as
institutional power uh you've got an
over
balancing and it's it's very extreme and
that's where we are right now
um as i said earlier the welfare states
in scandinavia had 85 percent of the
people in labor unions balancing
corporate power
we're down to six percent and declining
in the private sector
11 overall and declining so there's a
fundamental problem at the heart of the
system
on top of that is the constitutional
rigging that was set up
at the early days which you know in the
early days you had
no women couldn't vote and black slaves
couldn't vote
and men without property could not vote
in the early days of the american
constitution
so slowly property got moved out
and then women and then people who were
slaves
became unslaves and they could vote in
theory but in practice they were denied
the vote from
you know almost 100 years after the
civil war through
violence and suppression so the whole
question of voting
is part of a systemic design as well but
the big ones are institutional
what do you do about who gets to own
wealth
uh big corporations should they dominate
some people have argued we ought to have
a small competitive economic system the
chicago school of economics very
conservative
was very very for 40 years was very very
upset by the rise of the large
multinational corporation
these are conservative economists you
know very eminent conservative
economists at the chicago school of
economics
because the large corporation would deny
competition
they would work out deals with other
corporations
they would cut up the market they were
politically powerful
unlike small entrepreneurial competitive
capitalism
so you find a very strong critique of
corporate dominated capitalism which is
where we live now
coming from free-market folks in the
the great conservative school
so that's a different systemic design
in theory the old design was lots of
small competitive businesses would keep
liberty alive and also an efficient
economy
but that's over when the big big big
companies dominate markets
and control a form of competition that
doesn't look anything like free market
competition
so if you don't like the government
owning everything state socialism like
communism or the soviet union and you
don't want the corporations dominating
everything without and no labor unions
are they've been destroyed where are you
gonna go
and so that's a real question it's just
like the time of the constitution
what makes sense what would be the right
way to go
how would you design a system that
benefited everyone but also was very
sophisticated
about institutional power so that it
kept things in balance rather than get
swept away by technologies that would
promote centralization of corporate
or government power and that's what the
next system project is about and that's
what the book you're talking about what
then must we do
and several other books i've written and
and a number of uh
articles in our project and books coming
out of it
having a real debate about the systems
beyond the ones we know
are in trouble and practical debate and
experimentation
to get it away from rhetoric to say i
like the term architecture what's the
architecture
the american constitution is a
architectural design what would be a
better design
in the modern technological era that
would preserve
and and this is the test preserve these
values
liberty democracy equality ecological
sustainability and maybe even a sense of
community
what design would produce those results
in practice
and what do we know about that and what
how can we think about it so
that book what then must we do is just
one contribution to that debate
and our next system project is a
full-scale
as i say discussion and the conferences
we've had at major universities and
around the country our other
contributions
we're about to publish a big reader on
this edited by
my co-chair of the of this next system
project the gus
beth a rather eminent ecologist who was
the chairman he was also head of the
undp at the united nations
one of the big development projects uh
he's
uh and he and i run the next system
project which is producing
debating papers like the committee's
correspondence
and if you don't like the current system
you don't like the state socialism
communism
uh what makes sense how do we organize
the next system in a way that builds
community democracy ecological
sustainability
liberty um how do you do that and what's
a design it's just like the federalist
papers
debated the constitutional design
although they didn't get very far into
institutions because they assumed
small business and small farms except in
the south where it was all plantations
and small farms so they didn't get far
into economic institutions
mainly political institutions but we're
talking about economic as well as
political
design uh architecture and institutions
of a
new direction you know building out to
the next century
yeah definitely work that needs to be
done i like the fact that you take a
pragmatic approach
let's try some things you know
truthfully i'm skeptical
of high theory and that comes from my
study of complexity science since i
retired from the business world 20 years
ago i've been associated with the santa
fe institute and
i've gotten myself pretty educated on
the nature of complex adaptive systems
networks of networks non-linear dynamics
etc
and one of the things we learn from that
quantitative study
is that predicting the future evolution
of complex systems when you make a
change
is a hell of a lot harder than people
used to think
you know in fact i love the old john
maynard keynes quote
the ideas of economists and political
philosophers both when they are right
when they are wrong
are more powerful than it's commonly
understood indeed the world is ruled by
little else practical men who believe
themselves to be quite exempt from any
intellectual
influences are usually the slaves of
some defunct economist
and i think that's a warning to us all
to proceed pragmatically and by
experiment
and see what works but yet still proceed
with a plan and with as you called it a
north star
in mind yep well
i i totally agree as i matter of fact i
did my phd at cambridge at the
dominator keynesian college john maynard
keynes was the uh
king's college and he was a very good
investor as well and he made a lot of
money for king's college cambridge where
i
did my phd but his idea was was i
thought
right and and then he went later to
institutional questions what
you you can't you've got to try you have
to try things but you also have to have
a north star to keep revising the
direction as you try
but you can't avoid the theoretical
debate either you've got to do both
yep and you know in my business world i
used to call it pikes peak i
tell people there's pikes peak 200 miles
away no telling what swamps and rivers
and
hostile indian tribes are between us and
there
but if we know where we're going and
we're smart and we're pragmatic and
we're adaptive
we'll get there the same is true about
the future let's do a little side talk
here about
unions you mentioned sweden i looked up
the data
before the show and currently 67 percent
of swedes are members of unions
much higher than our six percent down a
little bit from the peak of 80 or 85
and it's interesting a friend of my wife
and i's i guess you could call them more
or less a swedish trumpet
very conservative both socially and
economically
nonetheless he's president of his local
union of firefighters
and anyone that would question the union
in his mind as a madman
even though he's very conservative even
in american terms let alone in swedish
terms
what happened to our unions as you point
out
they were the principal countervailing
force at least during that short period
of mass industrialization from say
1933 to maybe 1975 but
somehow they seemed to been captured by
their leadership they became corrupt
they became much more interested in
feather betting and holding on to jobs
rather than
co-evolving industry into a global
high-tech future
what went wrong with our unions and is
there any hope at all to recover them
well you know i would uh first i think
that that generalization is uh
probably doesn't apply to all the unions
uh because
that certainly doesn't apply to all the
unions there were some very
democratic unions there were some better
ones or some worse ones
so i would you know have a we'd go into
that in some detail
but in a certain sense what's much more
important
is they have technology and sectoral
change
and trade have essentially eliminated
most unions quite apart from the
problems you're talking about it within
the union structure
so let's put it this way you talked
about the swedish unions they were up at
the 80
mark and on down to 62 that's a powerful
powerful force to counter balance the
corporation
when you got that many people in unions
the united states
peaked at 34 of the labor force
organized
it's down to six percent in the private
sector
six tiny 11 if you include the the
teachers and the
folks in the public sector schools and
primarily schools but government
officials and government
administrators so that that the model
of a political economic system in which
power
is corporation based like sweden or like
the united states political power going
attached to large corporations
implicitly or explicitly
balanced by unions sort of kind of
to produce a welfare state compromise
that model was most advanced in
countries the scandinavian countries
you know bernie sanders likes to talk
about a little tiny one of them
which is denmark which is a tiny one and
sweden which is a little bit bigger
it was counterbalanced by strong unions
it's over in the united states the game
is over and i'm i'm
i'm supportive of unions i've always
been supportive of them because i think
you need to counterweight
but the fact is they're down to 11
10.8 last time i saw the numbers
probably a little bit different now
uh and it's a and declining so they are
very weak in most sectors uh school
teachers are perhaps
some of the best organized but in the
private sector they're not
minimal and so the corporations have all
the all the clout all the political
power
that's a different institutional
foundation institutionally
for a political economic system and it's
very dangerous because it does it's not
counter balanced
and i think in a sense uh
donald trump represents the
configuration of politics that comes out
of that
or worse i mean it's a it's a recipe for
fascism if violence occurs
and there's no labor organizing the
traditional response is to crush
the violence which makes makes politics
very very dangerous
uh leads to corporate states and politic
historically around the world
uh to something called fascism or
quasi-fascism
so unions have been very important in
about in balancing that direction
and uh we're very it's very dangerous
unless you can develop
and this is where where it gets kind of
interesting in terms of political
economic architecture and the future
go back and think about the committees
of correspondence and the founding of
the constitution they were debating
well they didn't know what to do about
the constitution they had to figure one
out no one had ever
figured out a democratic constitution
and indeed the
what's happening around the country in
many universities and in our next system
project
people are saying well if if the state
socialist model
soviet union doesn't work if liberalism
or social democracy the welfare state
doesn't work because labor unions are
declining which is the underpinning of
that system
where are we going to go particularly as
technology changes what's what's a smart
design what can we learn from history
what can we learn from other countries
what can we learn from theory what you
know and how do we debate this and how
do we get
experiments that teach us something and
indeed
that judgment and i say i work
as a very hands-on politics in the
house as a legislative director in the
house legislative director in the senate
policy planner in the state department
i've seen it all from the inside
and from the outside in politics but
also as an academic
well what makes sense how do we think
this through and
let's put some intelligence to this like
the committee of correspondence
so we've been having an ongoing research
debate
about systemic design publishing many
many papers
at the universities we're about about to
publish a compendium
uh edited by gustav speth my co-chair of
that
of the next system project uh we have
conferences on it and then we'll do
pieces of the puzzle
we'll talk about what do you do about
the energy system or what do you do
about the
public banks many many experimentation
a lot of experimentation with public
banks
if you want to see one one public bank
that most people don't
recognize the public bank but it has
been absolutely
gigantic in the current economic crisis
it's a federal reserve board which has
created trillions of dollars of
bailout in order to solve the crisis
so that's a particular piece of the
design that we don't even think about
it's been there so long but it has
enormous power in
the banking system so if you begin to
probe this stuff
it isn't as complex as it sounds if you
just begin to get into it and start
reading about it and start thinking
about it and having discussions
or experimenting locally there's a lot
of experimentation locally with
worker-owned companies
there's a really interesting model in
cleveland where it's a
neighborhood about 40 000 people with a
neighborhood non-profit corporation
to which are attached worker-owned
companies there's a there's a
electrical installation company for
solar installation there's one
there's big laundry ecologically stable
laundry
there's another companies they're all
worker-owned companies attached to
a community owned non-profit so that's a
complex mix that produces
something that is community benefiting
but also jointly with workers
and then if you use the big hospitals
like case western reserve hospital to
purchase
from this local complex that stabilizes
the local development form and it gives
you a model
that's quite interesting at the local
level uh in
in local communities and the biggest one
is in cleveland there's a big one in
in england that took off even more from
the cleveland model
in preston england experimenting with
new community models from the bottom up
there's discussion about public banks
from the top down in states
like the bank of north dakota one of the
most conservative states in the
country's got a 100 year old
publicly owned bank that small business
and farmers and everybody else is very
happy with in other states in california
and
washington state and new jersey have all
got movements trying to set up public
banks to
help support a new direction so there's
a lot of practical experimentation at
the same time people are
and let me challenge the word theorizing
they're trying to look at experience
with different models
and assess what we can learn from
partial experiences partial evidence of
capitalism socialism sustained socialism
what can we learn from those models
here's the test do they produce
democracy
some kind of equality liberty ecological
sustainability
and are they peaceful models what what
do we know about different models of
systemic design
and how do they measure up against
really important values so there's both
a
practical experimentation and then
there's a question about the comparative
in
knowledge and theory all of that and
i think that's you're going to see i
think you're going to see a lot of this
happening
more and more as the crisis deepens and
people like
trump illustrate what happens if you
don't take care of systemic design
yeah i think we'll get into soon a whole
series of these specific
cooperative and local ventures before we
do i'm going to pop up
a little bit one of them is going to
mention in passing i did the research on
unionization before the call and turns
out the sector with the highest rate of
unionization is actually the police
how about that right we know that that
is not
an unalloyed good in all cases well
there's
there's an interesting analogy because
i'm glad you raised that
uh jim there's a debate amongst
theorists
about community ownership and worker
ownership
as one piece of the puzzle and you know
that doesn't take care of big stuff and
corporations and regions and
state ownership and the question comes
up okay if you believe in
pure worker ownership as some theorists
do there's a whole bunch of folks say
the economy ought to be owned by
worker-owned companies entirely
and then you ask well um how would you
like the police force to be owned by the
police
and that's a worker-owned structure and
obviously the police have a different
interest than the community which has a
broader interest
so we have this concert we have the kind
of balancing of municipal
ownership of the police with worker
control
attempted control empowerment of police
unions
so a full worker-owned model would be
police ownership of the worker of the
police
system obviously that gives you an idea
of some of the
logical and theoretical problems in any
industry
does the community override does do you
want to have
the industry itself controlling
is that different for little companies
or big ones
when do you have to go to a public model
and how do you control
a democratic balance of power between
the workers in this case the police
and the community in this case the city
how do you set those balances so you've
got both experimental information
in many many countries and you also have
theoretical information about what where
the logic of it is
that's a perfect small scale example of
a next system
problem that we're an illustration of
what you have to think through at every
level
from small neighborhoods to police
systems to school systems
all the way up to what do you do about
the big corporations or big
state-owned industry like the tennessee
valley authority which is a
huge huge regional public enterprise for
energy that
the obama administration tried to get
rid of it by the way this is a
socialized enterprise in seven states
the tennessee valley authority
and then all the conservative senators
said no no no we like that they're
our our citizens want it the republicans
kept it alive
so it doesn't doesn't in practice
although you'd think it would go the
other way around in practice
uh some of these institutions have
support where you wouldn't expect it
yeah got good cheap power down the
tennessee valley that's why people want
it it works
it worked but then you've got the
conservative republicans
saying hey keep it there and the obama
administration is trying to get rid of
it
that's curious we talk about the scale
issue and you know
talk about the police union if you had
the police running the police
you'd have a mafia state in our game b
world
we've actually expropriated an idea
elsewhere i think the catholics
developed it originally called
subsidiarity and it's kind of central to
our thinking i noticed the book the word
did not appear in your book
and i have these cool power tools let me
search the full text of kindle books
which is kind of cool
that's appear in some of my other books
but that i guess i didn't remember
whether i used it there but i agree i
understand and agree that's an important
concept
yeah essentially it's for the audience's
sake that's essentially that says that
power should be devolved authority
should be devolved as far as possible
such that and this is the hard part such
that it is at the appropriate
level for resolution of the issues or
concerns right
for that reason you would not push
authority to govern the police to the
police
you would push it down one level above
that probably right
if you apply that concept as a lens it's
amazing how it
clarifies an awful lot of these
architectural questions
yeah include when i love you use the
term architectural
including the qualification that you
know in the police case for instance
if you push it all the way you go all
the way to the police organization
but obviously there's an other value
which is the community has an interest
in what they do so you have to move it
up a notch
so it's not an unqualified wherever the
technology suggests because there's a
different lens you have to look at in
terms of the implications for the whole
community
and there's also multi-dimensions right
you have one dimension you want law and
order
another dimension you want at the lowest
possible cost and the third dimension is
you want it to be done with respect for
people's civil rights right
and there's a tension between those
three which may actually lead to three
different
levels of authority and management over
the nexus of something called the police
this is a great example jim and i'm glad
you raised it because
what you are talking from the language
we use is systemic design
or constitutional design if there's
failings in the larger
dynamics of the overall country such
that they produce
conditions which end up electing a man
like the current president
there's something wrong with the design
in my view
and in many people's view but leaving
that aside if it produces
ecological destruction there's something
wrong with the design
if it produces uh huge numbers of
unemployed people and
drug problems and criminalization of
unemployed people is there something
wrong with the design
so if you ask it that way it can become
a very very clear set of questions to
ask what makes sense
not left right center up down what makes
sense including how do you preserve
liberty
those are real criteria to apply to the
question
and then the second question is if you
were clear about your design
this is you know the articles of
confederation versus the constitution
the debate in the federalist papers what
makes sense what doesn't make sense
then how do you experiment and also how
do you produce
a long-term evolutionary transformation
of the system
in the direction of what makes sense uh
that's what we're doing
that's the next system project and it
sounds like it it kind of intersects
with
what you were talking about at the uh at
the institute
yeah also in our game b world institute
provides the
complexity framework which you know
realizes that the world is very high
dimensional that everything is adaptive
and strategic
our game b efforts a separate effort
that then applies those insights and
others
into thinking about the social operating
system for the future
and as we'll get into here in a minute i
think we come up with some similarities
and perspectives
i'm going to read a quote here from your
book you know who the answer is the
audience probably won't but then you can
tell us who the author was
i can't help but believe that in the
future we'll see in the united states
and throughout the western world
an increasing trend towards the next
logical step
employee ownership it is a path that
befits
a free people i think that's ronald
reagan is it
it is it's ronald reagan right what kind
of raven lefty wrote that stuff right it
was
ronald reagan and there's always been a
strong
tendency in some parts of the
conservative movement
towards things like employee ownership
and suspicion for large corporations
as you said the chicago school you don't
get much more ideologically conservative
than men
they understand that you know there is a
tendency towards rent seeking what did
adam smith say
there's never a meeting of manufacturers
where the main point of discussion is a
conspiracy and restraint of trade right
so you know reagan says it employee
ownership that's one of the things that
you talk about you talk about
it in many forms and i think it'd be
useful for the audience to go
you know into some of these forums a
little bit and talk about them then we
can talk about some other
you know cooperative democratically
organized ways of delivering other kinds
of services like credit unions
mutual banks etc so let's start with
employee ownership
of a company talk to us about what some
of the mechanisms exist there
what's the status of that what are the
trends etc
let me start with the theoretical point
that you raised right there
at the outset because i think there's a
major there's very significant role for
employee-owned companies i like to say
worker-owned companies are because their
employee owned
they employ themselves when they own the
company
so it's a little odd but let's let's
start with that
example about because there's a
theoretical problem right at the heart
of what you mentioned earlier
think about the city government and the
municipality
and the police organization
worker ownership of the the institution
and enterprise called police force
would make it such that the workers in
that particular
sector the policemen would run that game
and they would be independent and that
would
constitute certain uh problems but a
pure worker ownership model in the
police industry
would give over to the workers of that
union
that total dominance now obviously it
doesn't make sense
because the community as a whole has a
stake in
what the police do and they set the laws
and they set the terms of reference
so a full model would be the
city municipal government would control
the police which
in theory it does but in practice the
police have a lot of political power
so it's kind of a mixed model and that's
a really good
paradigm kind of example of what would
you do
for instance with great big corporations
uh supposing you believe in worker
ownership of companies
do you really want the oil companies to
be owned by the oil workers
and have a stake in polluting the
environment and and
fighting climate change is that the
model you want
or does the community as a whole have an
interest in that that is greater than
the guys who happen to be working
in it at the moment and who never
created the oil in
in in the first place the oil was there
for centuries before they got there
so it's i'm not trying we could answer
that question but
it's a good example these two are really
good examples of the difference between
worker ownership
and community ownership or some kind of
balance system
and the pros and cons of each one have
to be sorted out and
that's a good system design challenging
question at
every level of society that needs to be
looked at just as the people who
designed the constitution began to
debate
exactly these kinds of questions yeah
and
my response to that would be frankly it
almost doesn't matter who
owns let's say an oil company whether
it's one guy
there are still a few family-owned oil
companies
whether it's a bunch of anonymous
shareholders and managed through some
executives or whether it's worker
ownership
an oil company still needs to be bound
with respect to externalities right so
so that's a different part of the
architecture we say that the atmosphere
is a commons and the commons
is managed by a different group than the
oil company
and so in a at least in the models that
we're we're working on
the commons that owns the air let's say
in this case it ought to be the world's
citizens and their designees should have
to agree
to allow pollution into their air you
know it's a little abstract but you get
the concept
and so that no single player should be
allowed to exploit externalities without
restraint
and that would be an architectural
failure if that was in the system
that's a really good example and let me
let me uh sharpen the issue from the
point of view of the next system project
because it's a really good question and
it's it comes up in the police
case and it also comes up in exactly the
case you mentioned the oil industry
in theory what you said is the larger
institution maybe the community or this
or the country should control the
oil so it doesn't destroy the commons
that the the
atmosphere and produce climate change
that was what you said right
correct i agree with that but and here's
the big but
but if the oil is owned by
either the workers or by private
corporations
in practice we know that they influence
and often overwhelm the community
structure through political
empowerment so that you don't get the
common result you want
by that design so it's a very very and
if you go state
if the state the government owns it all
as in the soviet union
instead of the workers or the oil
companies you've got another even worse
design
because the commons the government or
the state
doesn't give a damn and it pollutes as
well in that model
so now you're up against a really what
is the design
in powering the different groups at
stake that would actually produce the
result you want which is a fair
distribution of democracy
and climate stability
it's a very it's not a sim it's not a
simple either or just
in the way you posed it i think you i'm
sure you know that for the work
that you folks do at the institute it
gets more complex because it doesn't
quite work so well because
there's a feedback loop between the
power of the local
corporations or the unions and the
government that's supposed to control
them that doesn't quite work the way we
think it would work so you're really up
against
the next system problem in its most
powerful way how do we do what do we do
how do we make it work that that would
overcome these two problems
or and again police is a perfect example
just like the oil companies
is there's they have a hand in
controlling the city government
in politic in politics sometimes or in
controlling the
people who control the environment in
terms of climate change
the oil union and the oil companies are
not
independent of that they try to control
the regulatory status so it isn't quite
separate in the in the way we think of
it
and that's the that's the democratic
theory problem that
writ large that's that's the heart of
the system question
right in fact at our very beginnings of
our game b examinations
the first thing that came up in our
analysis was exactly what you're talking
about is that
in a way that's accelerated very rapidly
over the last 50 years
the linkage between economic power and
political power has now become
at least until very recently maybe
reversing with this populist trend but
at least until the last four or five
years
political power and economic power very
tightly interwoven
and that any architectural design needs
to break the linkage between
money and politics and the solution we
came up with i'd love to get your
thoughts on this as a person who's
thought about architecture
is to absolutely ban both political
advertising
and issue advertising that's funded by
any other source
other than what we call political money
every citizen would get a bank account
and in that account they'd get a hundred
dollars a year if you add that all up
that comes up to
30 billion dollars that's a lot of money
for being political
and only that money could be used for
either issue advocacy
or political advertising and so then
you'd still have the benefits
of incremental voting with money
and yet nobody would have outside impact
on the political process
so what what's what's interesting about
what you said
let me go to the abstract question and
then the practical question
that's a particular design and that's
what the next system project is all
about
how do we evaluate different designs
would they or would they not produce the
desired outcome
so that and that's the kind of thing we
do in the next system project and is
what would we actually work in practice
so let me go to the substance of that it
isn't entirely clear to me that
if you did that it might it certainly
would increase
citizen help and citizen participation i
and
it would help i think i i would before i
would support what you're saying
that said as someone who has worked in
both houses of congress
and in the executive branch the power
institutionally
day by day by day minute by hour by hour
of lobbyists coming up day by day
by day bringing new plans writing the
legislation
targeting money into the different
political realms is a
institutional force that manages
the leverage of the money so it's not
quite as abstract if everybody had money
to contribute
that's one thing but the institutional
power of how they utilize
political power is associated to like
the oil companies
and the oil unions by the way and the
police unions
uh even if people have money to
contribute to campaigns
so the mechanism you describe and we
get without without saying how you come
down on what i think would be a positive
but there are underlying institutional
forces that might undermine
that mechanism so these we're now we're
right in the middle of the
system project debating exactly exactly
this is the debate at every level what
would work and of course to your point
yes you'd have to also ban the oil
companies from
funding from corporate sources you know
citizens united st who's the who
who's the you would have to and how do
you control the you
who is that actually in practice it
becomes a question
yeah again it's another question right
that's the democratic constitution et
cetera
by what mechanism does this get done
yeah
and and how do you ensure that the you
as a democratic you
because there's an awful lot of you know
when i worked in as i say on the hill in
the house and senate
uh the oil companies would come in with
the lobbyists and
three piece suits and tons of campaign
contributions and lots of
well-designed legislation already worked
out you could just use it tomorrow
with a speech attached to it and here's
a draft senator he wanted to use this
raft to write it anyway you know that
it's it's much more detailed and complex
when you actually see it in practice
yep again that's why you'd have to ban
them from doing that right
who's the you the political system
i.e legislation who designs the
legislation who enforces it that's the
problem because you get back to the same
people they're going to say no we're not
going to let you pass that legislation
now that's the problem of course and why
it may or may not be feasible from a
purely democratic perspective
that's the problem what is the design
that would allow you to
do these things at every level rather
than wouldn't it be nice if
yeah if i were the dictator i could do
it this way right of course it would
never end there because we know
dictatorship never ends well right
exactly
so you're referring back to these all
these these wonderful questions
and but there are answers to it a lot of
experimentation and
i don't want to make it overly complex
and you can see it in your own city
whether where there's
citizen action begins to get into the
picture uh so theoretical problems
practical problems and there's
experiments in everyday life
yeah let's talk about some of those
experiments you mentioned a whole bunch
of them
you know things like again different
forms of worker-owned
enterprises co-ops for instance we've
looked at co-ops quite a bit
in fact my wife and i are a member of
three co-ops two agricultural co-ops
we're farmers
amongst other things and we belong to a
food co-op
as an example and then we've also looked
into
and we think this is a perhaps a wave of
the future worker-owned co-ops that have
hybrid financial structures
one of the things that's held back
worker-owned co-ops historically it's
been relatively difficult to aggregate
very much capital so it's okay for a
relatively
low capital intensity business i think
one of the examples you gave is actually
a good one
you know senior care co-op owned by the
people who deliver the services
but even at the level of a grocery store
the amount of money
necessary to launch that food co-op
really forced them for it to be a
purchaser co-op which in my mind is
quite a bit less
empowering than a worker-owned co-op and
to be able to do worker-owned co-ops you
need a hybrid financial structure
unfortunately there's work going on
there
which allows low to moderate rate or
return capital invested typically as
debt or preferred stock
while still keeping the one employee one
vote rules for the co-ops so that you
can aggregate enough capital
to actually do a worthy business like a
grocery store or let's say an industrial
commercial laundry service etc
well let me it's a good question because
um
i'm i'm originally from wisconsin which
is there's a lot of a lot of co-ops in
wisconsin
agricultural and other co-ops and of
various kinds
and we're now talking primarily about
worker ownership co-ops rather than a
consumer co-op
or a kind of credit union which is
another form of co-op
the fact is historically it's been all
but impossible to get beyond
one or two or three or four percent of
the labor force
in worker-owned co-ops of any kind
that's just a fact uh in
in of history in around the world so
if there's a real question of how far
that particular design
can go that's step one step two
is worker-owned businesses and there's
been a number of studies we've done
we've accumulated 30 or 40 studies on
this
tend to produce unexpectedly
attitudes that are quite kind of
politically
conservative against social program they
they generate because they're businesses
and
consumer co-ops are a little different
but worker-owned co-ops
uh tend to go back to well we're a
business we've gotta
fight for a business place and in
practice
the studies that have been developed by
and large and i want to say by and large
because
they're they're not that many but they
tend not to go in the direction of
cooperation
as a public value but rather how do you
preserve businesses as a business value
so that's just the fact of the design
produces that outcome so far as we know
in general so then the worker co-op
becomes a form of
essentially one person one vote
capitalism and as the model even though
it's called a cooperative
in terms of its political attitude
structure
external to the world which is quite
surprising we've had a someone has
surveyed the last
60 or 70 studies of this and that turns
out to be
what we've learned so far that doesn't
mean
more complex models mondragon in spain
is more complex model
which subsumes worker ownership within a
larger communitarian
structure of with a different in this in
this case
catholic theological base might produce
a different internal culture
but in fact the model that you were
talking about so far as we've been able
to see it doesn't produce the result
that we would like to see
coming from wisconsin where we all have
lots of co-ops
i like co-ops but i don't see them
worker co-ops
and even though i support them and
wherever you can do it i don't think
there are systemic
direction for the whole system yep
that's probably the case
again one of our theories is that unless
there's other countervailing forces
people
operate in their own self-interest right
so if you're a worker co-op embedded in
a doggy dog capitalist culture
then either you behave in a somewhat
dog-eat-dog fashion or you get eaten
that's right and that's the problem
that's the problem of a market system
that's what we call the race to the
bottom dynamic right it's not
necessarily of a market system
yeah market systems have some attributes
of that but there's any kind of
race to the bottom dynamics i'll give
another example of a race to the bottom
dynamics which isn't
really a market driven phenomena and
that is when the big companies like
walmart play two towns off against each
other
on where they're going to locate the
next warehouse in fact the little town
where we spend some time it's about an
hour from our farm we have a little
condo there
they got snookered by walmart big time
they played our little town of stanton
off against another town waynesboro
where this distribution warehouse was
going to be
and they got a 20-year tax abatement
walmart you know one of the biggest the
biggest company in the world i guess
by some measures not by market cap but
by a number of employees etc
i got a 20-year tax abatement from a not
very prosperous small town in virginia
by being played off in a race at a
bottom dynamic against one of their
you know peer towns down the road 10
miles right
when we open these questions these are
suspect from our point of view these are
system design questions
what do we know about what can we learn
about this what do we learn about these
dynamics
even in the case of cooperatives which i
come out
i'm sort of prejudiced in the favor of
cooperatives in principle
but we've been studying them rather
closely and and they don't the results
are not
quite what you would expect either they
don't scale or often they run into some
of the dynamics that the market forces
on them
what are some thoughts you all have
let's address that problem
just think out loud here and maybe
thoughts you guys have had
about let's say we have a worker-owned
cooperative or any kind of business
actually
how do we get around this race to the
bottom dynamic
well the the models that i've been
interested in
uh and they're not i haven't seen too
many perfect ones in practice but
the original model that was being
developed in cleveland
was a community-wide non-profit
corporation one person one vote
in a neighborhood of 40 000 non-profit
corporation
to which were attached worker-owned
companies
subordinated to the non-profit
corporation
and the theory was that in practice the
workers would be able to organize
politically as well as institutionally
but they would be
countervailed to use john kenneth
galbraith's idea
by a community representative structure
representing the whole community's
environment for instance
the whole community's interest in kind
of good health of the community as a
whole
a variety of community where the jobs
would be placed
there would be a community interest but
there would be some sort of
countervailing balance
now that model in practice in particular
in cleveland
turned out to be in in practice it ended
up more a worker ownership model than
what i just described in practice but
the model in theory that we've been
looking at for futures
how do you give where in what cases do
you want community control
police is another example obviously
would you want a police
union to control the police business
no obviously no you want the police
business to be
subordinated to the non-profit
corporation we call city government
that scares the interest of the whole
community in line
and keeps the police subordinated to
that in their business
uh so that it doesn't overwhelm the
whole community
so that balancing problem is really
important
and then there's a secondary feedback
loop and you see it everywhere you see
the police unions operating
they become big in the politics of the
city
so they come around and say well you may
control us at the city government level
but by and large we're going to elect
the guys we want we're going to
influence them and con contribute so
they they don't control
us the way you want to control us so so
what is the answer to that feedback loop
problem
you now we are right at the heart of a
good example of system design
and i think you know we be how to
balance these interests how do you
create uh
judicial power that manages some of this
and we're seeing that at the national
level where
the political system by biases the
judicial system
these abstract questions become very
practical in the debate
as as happened during the constitutional
period when people are debating what the
constitution should look like
these are the inherent problems that we
need to flesh out and work and debate
and one other one to add to it as
technology goes forward
we are practically speaking could be a
society of
very little work time at work because
the technology could
already produce very good incomes if it
were distributed properly
for the vast majority of the 20-hour
week already
but it's all concentrated at the top and
in ways that are not so
but as we go forward in the rest of the
century the technological projections
are for
the possibility of radically reduced
work time
if we can if we can manage it
politically which means that people will
be free of their
interest group companies they'd be free
as citizens rather than
sort of well i'm an oil worker i want
the oil company to work or i'm a police
guy i want the police to work
they will be less less dominated by
their work
condition uh technology is moving in
that direction
already and if we can organize ourselves
institutionally to
to manifest and kind of exploit the
wonderful possibilities that technology
offers
rather than distribute it all to the top
um you're going to have a society where
there's a lot of free time to do
kind of politics free of institutional
pressures
or substantially free so that's a whole
other dimension to add to the debate
we're right in the middle of the next
system project debate these are the
kinds of questions that we're trying to
weigh
and this one of course is an absolute
key one right we're at the cusp
in my other part of my life i work in
artificial intelligence at the highest
end you know where we're looking to
reach human levels and beyond
and it'll happen whether it's 40 years
or whether it's 10 years
maybe it's as long as 60 years i'd be
surprised if it's any longer than that
and if if this is managed correctly this
could be an amazing
boon for humanity like it's never seen
before right
in fact a friend of mine calls it
automated luxury communism
right and free time yeah exactly that's
what i would think
hopefully people especially if we can
deprogram people a little bit from
thinking that he who dies with the most
toys wins and status through possessions
our game b movement has a lot of ideas
about that which we'll talk about in a
little while
this may be a huge opportunity but as
you point out
that if the current hyper-financialized
corporate operating system
remains unchanged essentially it'll mean
the rich will get way richer than
you can possibly imagine well everybody
else is pressed down
pretty far and gets no benefit from this
or very little
right but but for the first time in
history really the technology
is moving in the direction of permitting
freedom from the
the work demand or much more free time
so
that's a really interesting development
though it's interesting keynes predicted
it that we'd be working 15 hours a day
by now and that that didn't happen
but it technologically is is available
technologically this hasn't been
available politically
yeah and psychologically right we're
programmed to want
more more more more right fancier
shinier we need a whole cultural system
in addition to an economic system
so that we have a high quality of life
without this
intense and relentless focus on status
through possessions
well now that takes you to the design of
community culture
yes so the in the emphasis in the book
that you
you've been talking about the what then
must we do and the emphasis in a lot of
work i do and i'm
doing a new book on the subject is how
do you generate
the conditions that produce a more
community culture
that reflects the values that you just
articulated
how do you actually think about that in
terms of systemic design
over and then what's the path what's the
you know
you can't plunk that down what are
developmental paths that move in the
direction of a design that might
encourage
broader community vision and community
understanding
uh the reflection of each and each
other's eyes as equal
as the philosophers put it
that's another factor in the systemic
design question
how do you do that if you're at santa fe
institute an old friend of mine sam
bowles has been experimenting and kind
of studying that question
uh in micro situations um
i i don't know if you've seen some of
his work on that oh yes i've read a lot
of his work fact sam's gonna be on the
show next month oh good well give him my
best
i certainly will yeah sam's one of my
favorite people hibbing has worked with
herb guintas yeah
irv and sam are old friends of mine they
were part of something called the
cambridge institute
long ago in cambridge that i was deeply
involved in
yeah i think they have shown reasonably
convincingly that the theory that homo
economicus is the natural state of homo
sapiens
is actually just plain wrong and that
there is a lot of
baked in libido for cooperation
and to some degree altruism that with
good
institutional design we can build a
society that isn't dog eat dog
yep yep i agree they've done great work
and sam's last book is really
interesting on this
yeah i haven't read it yet but i'm going
to read it for his podcast
about the incentives with where folks
drop off their kids or pick up their
kids at the nursery
school in israel there's a wonderful
passage there that
he really illustrates some of the things
you're talking about yeah in fact that's
funny one of the areas that we've been
studying is kibbutz's in fact i had a
expert on kibbutz on the show last month
in fact he show just came out today
and it's really quite interesting send
me the link i'm interested i
spent a lot of time studying the books
many many many years ago
yeah this is rand abraham itzke from
stanford
the book is the mystery of the kibbutz
and there's a full episode up on it
right now on my website so
i'll send you the link and what he does
is essentially compare and contrast
classic western stanford economics
department
analysis on what people should do
versus what actually happened in the
kibbutz and what he found
which is interesting is the original
kibbutz's were set up on a radical
egalitarian basis
everybody got exactly the same material
well-being in their life
whether they were the lawyer or the
person to clean the toilets
and yet economic analysis homo economica
style would say ah you should see
adverse selection the worst workers will
want to become members of your kibbutz
you'll get brain drain your best workers
will leave
you'll get shirking etc and it's
interesting he showed that yes some of
those things do exist but the kibbutz's
had developed at least partial solutions
for those
tendencies then he gets into very
interestingly what happened in the
kibbutz is after 1977 and when the likud
government cut off a lot of the
economic support that they've been
providing under the labor government
and at that time the kibbutz's started
differentiating there they're still
about 20 percent
they're still hardcore egalitarian
there's another fraction that might as
well be and rand incorporated right
and there's a lot in the middle more
like sweden or even a little bit more
welfare status than sweden so it's an
extraordinarily interesting
found experiment the middle one's called
the moshav set to v
yes for a brief period of time had all
that in my mind right
i read not only ryan's book but howard
near's two books on the history of
kibbutz's as well
let's move on to another topic we're
getting a little short on time here
which is you talk a fair amount about
municipally owned
utilities municipal smart land
development practices etc
why don't we talk about that a little
bit as a building block of systems
architecture
yes because that's a really interesting
question because the municipal
government
is a one-person one-vote uh corporation
and when should it be the dominant
controlling figure in a public utility
for instance
where we see that's the most common
place you see it
also if you want to see the balance
between worker ownership
and community ownership it's the city
municipal government versus the worker
control
piece of it called the police unions or
the police
group so what at what scale is
municipality
and let me let me let me go slightly
different
and the neighborhood in big cities
because there's a whole
whole developmental period of
neighborhood corporations
when in a big city might the
neighborhood or
the city in a small city like my
original home in wisconsin a city of
about 80 000
when do you think that's a useful place
to put some industry like the public
utility
should that be a city unit or should
that be private in the small cities or
big cities
and in very big cities how do you break
up neighborhoods and there was a big
movement towards neighborhood
incorporation
in the 60s and 70s and some cities like
atlanta and
and also seattle still have strong
neighborhood corporations
that are kind of subsidiaries of the
city government
but partly controlled by the
neighborhood so you get into
at what level of scale of industry and a
scale of community
is appropriate to different forms of
ownership
that in this case our community so they
represent the whole community
as opposed to just the workers like the
police workers
or even the the people who work in the
candy industry or the
oil industry so if you gave you want to
give the oil companies over to the oil
workers
then rather than the community as a
whole either the state or city or
national or the region as in the
tennessee valley authority
if you give the oil industry over to the
ownership of the workers in the oil
industry or the businesses in the oil
industry
their their interest is polluting the
country because that's going to be very
much to their advantage financially
so where do you structure these are
these are the questions of the next
system project where do you actually
would you want to structure
the design of different scale industries
in a way that benefits everybody and all
the parties at interest but particularly
the community as a whole
in any community this is really a big
point for most people don't think about
the workers involved of working age
work leaving aside the old people
leaving aside the sick people
leaving aside the kids who are in school
leaving all those aside
you're talking 40 or 50 percent of the
community are quote
the workers well you can't have a
community without the mothers bringing
up kids and
and running homesteads etc etc but so
worker ownership
and dominance in politics as some people
advocate
in worker-owned systems
what do you do about the rest of the
people who of any specific community
at all ages so there's a whole that's
another variable in systemic design
i don't want to make it overly complex
because i i would resort to the
community framework as a beginning point
and then to modify it
let's move on to another topic you know
how do we get this done
right you know you quote antonio gramsci
if that's how you pronounce it gramsci
about the problem of cultural and
ideological
hegemony which margaret thatcher called
tina there is no alternative somehow the
idea that's gotten in people's head that
the current way of doing things is the
only way of doing things
how do we get people to open their ears
to an alternative
well i'm uh you know spent half my time
as a historian
so i'm i'm reasonably optimistic about
that problem
if you view it historically you know to
put it in kind of equipped
systems come and go historically i mean
the world was
dominated by tribes and and feudalism at
one point in kings and
and churches and the feudal systems uh
and nobles and no votes um
somehow people got the vote i
i think over time we're talking about an
evolutionary
development from the bottom up where
people be feel more and more empowered
locally that's why the local things are
so important that they're in everyday
experience
building models through time that alter
the way in which the institutions are
structured
so if you want to play this game i
sometimes tell you know some of our
staff or students when i was
a university professor you have to throw
decades on the table
system change is about the
transformation of
institutions over periods of time now we
don't have
governments much mon run by kings and
feudal lords anymore
but if you'd like ask that question
during that period they'd say you can't
change it because it's impossible
so i'm a cautious optimist about
long-term development of new
consciousness and new institutions
but i often say to people you want to
play this game the price is decades of
your life on the table to work on this
kind of change
like the women's movement did like the
labor movement did
like the civil rights movement did like
the environmental movement did
all of which had huge long decade by
decade periods before they actually
start making change
and i think that's the nature of the
game so i am a
cautious optimist as as an economist
political economist and as a historian
about transformative possibilities but i
do not think you
should play the game in the if you think
it can be done overnight there's a lot
of developmental work to do
and why experiments are really important
at certain stages
and political movements and institution
building
i think this is i think it's a very
creative moment in american history by
the way we've been
we've been studying all these
experiments on the ground that the press
doesn't have the resources to cover
so i think there's a huge amount out
there which we put on our websites
all the time but uh but it's a long
process and
and uh you shouldn't play you don't you
shouldn't play this game
if you think you can do it overnight or
you should just make a small
contribution
the name of the game is to look at
people like like the
supreme court justice who just passed
who
spent decades of her life working for
women's and feminist rights
that's true in civil rights uh we also
disliked lost john lewis decades of work
uh labor rights decades of work uh
that's the name of the game
uh but but from that framework as a
historian rather than as a political
theorist
i'm cautiously optimistic about the uh
as martin luther king
said the the the the arc of history
moves towards equality and but maybe a
long arc
uh or at least it is worth a good fight
that's i think a very healthy way to
look at i'm always very skeptical
that people think they can go in the
streets and suddenly the world's going
to change
sorry doesn't usually work that way and
when it does work that way it's not
usually a change for the better if we
look at our history right
yep totally agree totally agree i told i
call the process
evolutionary reconstruction as opposed
to revolution
or reform reform assumes the existing
institutions you got to clean them up
around the edges
but changing system is an evolutionary
process if it's going to get anywhere
in fact let's move now to our last topic
as we're getting close to our
90 minute time you basically i love this
as a person who likes to think about
strategy and think a little deeply and
aren't afraid of relatively complex
interrelationships you lay out a
four-part path forward
doesn't quite well let you say what's
else is missing but
essentially you have four parts an
evolutionary reconstruction idea
the checkerboard strategy very clever
i'd never heard that before i never even
thought that thought but reading that
thought
gives me a new tool crisis
transformations
and then big crisis transformations
maybe you could take us through those
four
and how you see those moving us towards
this better future
well evolutionary reconstruction is what
we've begun to talk about in the
experiments with worker-owned companies
and community worker companies like in
cleveland and preston english with
community-wide
corporations to which are subordinated
worker companies
there's a lot of evolutionary
experimentation with new forms
that's one second as opposed to class
struggle which is you know conservatives
versus liberals
there's a lot of experimentation in what
i call a checkerboard
you can find really interesting examples
in western texas
of quite interesting community
cooperatives
uh you can find them in atlanta you can
find them
in uh rochester new york where there's a
really complex
fight going on with the unions so
there's a whole checkerboard of
experimentation
uh and one of the things to say about
this is that the press doesn't cover a
lot of this stuff at the grassroots
level
they really don't have the resources or
interest in doing it because
most newspapers are financed by
advertising to people who can
pay money and so the stories that are
written are
not really about what's going on in poor
communities or working-class communities
or they're undercovered so but there's a
lot of experimentation
on the checkerboard side of this uh all
over the country we cover that on our
web pages we know
and we follow it so we know that there's
so much more going on
that you would really it's a wonderful
period of experimentation
it's like the 1920s when in the what was
called the quote
laboratories of of democracy the states
the states around the country
experiments were going on that during
the new deal became the
sketches upon which the new deal built a
lot of the new deal models
and i think a lot of that's happening in
these these different parts
of the system give me the other two
categories i'm i'm blocking in
the last two categories that that you
mentioned crisis transformation and
big crisis transformation yeah the
the there's a good example of crisis
transformation
uh in two different levels the great
depression which is a very different
process from little
experiments building up over time to be
bigger experiments
here and there around the checkerboard a
crisis transformation was
collapse of the system producing for
instance
the social security system and the labor
laws that's a whole different process
that allows a qualitative shift in the
systemic
design that's a crisis transformation
and it was not a total transformation it
was only a partial transformation
a much larger transformation might occur
if there were sufficient institutional
and cultural buildings on the ground
that laid the foundations
for something that was far beyond one or
two sectors
the new deal was from the point of view
of the system
is still a corporate capitalist system
very weak
welfare state compared with sweden for
instance it's a dominant
still a dominant corporate corporate
system a
big systemic crisis might or might not
achieve
a revolution uh and often that's not the
best
way of transforming because it often
involves violence and repression and a
long time for getting out from under
that
system but those are the different
models over time
and and another way to think about it is
the transformative
period like you i often say to the
younger people you want to play this
game you got to throw a few decades of
your life on the table
10 20 30 40 year time spans
the way of thinking about transformation
is neither
a revolution kind of horizontally
splitting society and turning it upside
down
the workers take over uh nor exactly a
reform
where the corporations control
everything and you try to clean it up
around the side
that's the welfare state or the social
democratic model
but an evolutionary reconstruction is
kind of like
in geology where the rock formations
slide over each other
up one from the bottom over
transformative
so there's enough building up from the
bottom that begins to transform
the larger pattern over time
institutionally
and at some point there's a culmination
of this building process
that makes for a qualitative shift as
well as a quantitative shift
and i think it's that set of processes
rather than a classic
revolution or a classic oval of the
liberals or
conservatives and things will happen
those are secondary features of a larger
transformative process coming in from
the bottom up
in my view thing i like about that is
it's realistic
one can imagine you know doing all four
of these things doing experiments at the
local level
building patterns of them around and one
of the things you didn't quite mention i
don't think is that the checkerboard
strategy
has the interesting advantage that
assuming again the experiments work is
they provide
local examples to people about yes it is
possible
to do things differently and then when a
crisis occurs
people are more willing to try these
different things and then when there's a
big
crisis then there's even more
willingness to try things but they're
more willing to try things if they've
been demonstrated at least at some
at a smaller scale than they are based
on some goddamn intellectual pinheads
ideas if you know what i mean right
with the exception of the i mean i think
there's a role for theory
that's what you and i have been talking
about this whole conversation
but in general i totally agree with what
you say and i think that i call it
evolutionary reconstruction
of the checkpoint strategy including
those four
models and i think that's um you know
that's a hopeful line of development
that uh we can pursue and are pursuing
that a lot of people are doing that
stuff on the ground now
matt in the last i've been working on
this kind of thing for you know
many many years since sam boze and herb
guintas and i were involved in the
cambridge institute back in the 60s
uh the models that have emerged around
the country and around the world
in the last 50 years are extraordinary
developments upon which you can really
begin to see
a transformative path uh and a lot of
hard work and a lot of and
you know don't play this game unless you
want to throw a few decades on the table
but it's but i think the the arc of
history of martin luther king said once
said
uh is long but it i think it probably
bends towards
equality over time let's hope
but i'm i'm encouraged by all the
experimentation we see in all the
developmental processes we see
below the below the horizon of what most
newspapers cover
unfortunately yeah that is a damn shame
hopefully we get a little publicity here
for your efforts
people can check it out on the episode
page at jimrutshow.com there'll be links
to everything we discussed here
and gar i'd really like to thank you
this has been a remarkably interesting
conversation i'd like to thank you for
the work you've been doing this is
important stuff
oh thank you jim it's a good
conversation
uh i can see you're into this game these
sets of questions
deeply as well and so it's good to talk
with someone who's thinking seriously
about this
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at modern space
music dot com